





C V n CURRÍCULUM VÍTAE NORMALIZADO



María Fernández Míguez

Generated from: Editor CVN de FECYT Date of document: 12/01/2022

v 1.4.3

bfc9d8aef6b26b9a8c3111d25091a480

This electronic file (PDF) has embedded CVN technology (CVN-XML). The CVN technology of this file allows you to export and import curricular data from and to any compatible data base. List of adapted databases available at: http://cvn.fecyt.es/





Summary of CV

This section describes briefly a summary of your career in science, academic and research; the main scientific and technological achievements and goals in your line of research in the medium -and long- term. It also includes other important aspects or peculiarities.

María Fernández Míguez, graduated in Biology from the University of Santiago de Compostela (USC). During her graduate degree, she collaborated for two years with the research group "Biodiversity, Biogeography and Invertebrate Conservation" (BIBICI) in the development of the complete taxonomy of different species of Terrestrial Gastropods of the Iberian Peninsula, this being part of her final work. race. Her MSc Aquaculture at said university was awarded the extraordinary academic award. During her master's degree he collaborated in the "Marine Genetic Resources Group" (ReXenMar) of the University of Vigo (Uvigo) and the "AguaCOV" group of the Spanish Institute of Oceanography (IEO-CSIC) as part of her master's final project, focused on the phylogeny of the genus Merluccius, thus obtaining knowledge in bioinformatics and different methods of phylogenetic reconstruction. This work formed the beginning of her doctoral thesis, during which she collaborated for three months with the company NOFIMA AS (Tromso, Norway) to analyze the morphological and genetic markers that influence the quality of Atlantic cod (Gadus morhua) egg. Her doctoral thesis allowed her to develop her knowledge in aquaculture, experimental design and gene expression analysis, which she complemented with teaching (support staff) and scientific dissemination. Among the science dissemination activities carried out during her thesis, it is worth highlighting the creation of the dissemination event "Marathon: 8 minutes of marine dissemination".





María Fernández Míguez

Surname(s): Fernández Míguez

Name: María DNI: 39460015L

ORCID: **0000-0002-9465-5467**

ScopusID: 57224438039 ResearcherID: ABH-1240-2020 Date of birth: 09/01/1993 Gender: **Female** Nationality: **Spain** Country of birth: **Spain** Aut. region/reg. of birth: Galicia Contact province: **Pontevedra** City of birth: Redondela Contact address: Pizarro 16 6F

Postcode: 36204
Contact country: Spain
Contact aut. region/reg.: Galicia
Contact city: Vigo

Email: mariafernandezm@uvigo.es

Mobile phone: (+34) 647855534

Personal web page: http://rexenmar.webs.uvigo.es

Previous positions and activities

	Employing entity	Professional category	Start date
1	University of Vigo	PhD candidate and researcher Xunta de Galicia	31/07/2017
2	University of Vigo	Collaborating staff in research and development	01/05/2017

1 Employing entity: University of Vigo

Professional category: PhD candidate and researcher Xunta de Galicia

2 Employing entity: University of Vigo

Professional category: Collaborating staff in research and development **Start-End date:** 01/05/2017 - 30/07/2017 **Duration:** 6 months







Education

University education

1st and 2nd cycle studies and pre-Bologna degrees

1 University degree: Higher degree

Name of qualification: Interuniversity Master in Aquaculture

Degree awarding entity: University of Santiago de Compostela

Date of qualification: 14/02/2017

2 University degree: Higher degree

Name of qualification: Graduated in Biology

Degree awarding entity: University of Santiago de Compostela

Date of qualification: 13/07/2015

Doctorates

Doctorate programme: Official Doctoral Program in Methodology and Applications in Life Sciences

Degree awarding entity: Faculty of Biology, University of Vigo

Date of degree: 19/11/2021

Language skills

Language	Listening skills	Reading skills	Spoken interaction	Speaking skills	Writing skills
English	B2	B2	B2	B2	B2
Gallegan	C1	C1	C1	C1	C1

Teaching experience

General teaching experience

1 Name of the course: Advanced Techniques in Biology

University degree: Graduated in Biology

Start date: 01/09/2018 **End date**: 30/09/2020

Entity: University of Vigo Type of entity: University Department

Faculty, institute or centre: Biology

2 Name of the course: Genetics II

University degree: Graduated in Biology

Start date: 01/09/2017 **End date:** 30/09/2017

Entity: Universidty of Vigo Type of entity: University Department





Faculty, institute or centre: Biology

Healthcare experience

Other activities/achievements not included above

1 Other relevant activities: Training activity on scientific dissemination "Ciencia de ida e volta"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 03/12/2021

2 Other relevant activities: Training course on science dissemination of The Conversation

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 26/10/2021

3 Other relevant activities: Scientist meet artist, "Que achega a xenética á trazabilidade das pescadas?

Entity where project took place: Marine Research Center (CIM)

End date: 08/06/2021

4 Other relevant activities: Science dissemination talk "How to become a researcher"

Entity where project took place: Colegio Santiago Apóstol

End date: 26/03/2021

5 Other relevant activities: Science dissemination talk "Aquaculture, how can we improve what we eat?"

Entity where project took place: Santiago Apóstol school

End date: 26/03/2021

6 Other relevant activities: Science dissemination talk "On the trail of COVID-19"

Entity where project took place: Santiago Apóstol school

End date: 26/03/2021

7 Other relevant activities: Science dissemination talk "Researchers vs climate change"

Entity where project took place: Santiago Apóstol school

End date: 26/03/2021

8 Other relevant activities: Science dissemination talk "How to become a researcher"

Entity where project took place: CEIP Fonte Escura school

End date: 19/02/2021

9 Other relevant activities: Traning course "Tecnoloxías Ómicas: Variant Calling Using NGS Data"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 22/11/2019

10 Other relevant activities: Training course "Writing and dissertation of the doctoral thesis"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 14/11/2019







11 Other relevant activities: Organization and creation of the dissemination contest "MARatón: 8 minutes of marine

research"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 08/05/2019

12 Other relevant activities: Research disseminative talk "Hakes of the world: clarifying the phylogenetic status of

five candidate species", ciclo de conferenciasCafé con Sal

Entity where project took place: Mariña Research Center (CIM)

End date: 05/02/2019

13 Other relevant activities: Participation in school visits to the Oceanographic Institute of Vigo to celebrate

Aquaculture Day

Entity where project took place: Spanish Institute of Oceanography

End date: 30/11/2018

14 Other relevant activities: Training course "Introduction to transcriptome and proteomic data analysis"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 29/11/2018

15 Other relevant activities: Training course "Crafting good communication skills: talks and posters"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 27/11/2018

16 Other relevant activities: Seminar "From the ocean to the laboratory: marine genetic resources and their

application in the production of new bioactive molecules"

Entity where project took place: Technological Center of the Sea

End date: 09/11/2018

17 Other relevant activities: Face-to-face course on innovation and sustainability in the aquaculture sector. Good

practices, new technologies and eco-efficiency

Entity where project took place: Toralla Marine Science Station

End date: 25/10/2018

18 Other relevant activities: Course "DNA Barcoding and Barcode of Life Data-system"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 26/09/2018

19 Other relevant activities: Participation in the project "Oceanic: women and oceanography"

Entity where project took place: Spanish Institute of Oceanography

End date: 20/09/2018

20 Other relevant activities: Training course "Statistical quality control with R"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 31/05/2018

21 Other relevant activities: First prize in the science dissemination contest "We are Scientists"

Entity where project took place: We are Scientists - FECYT

End date: 30/04/2018







22 Other relevant activities: Extraordinary Master's Award in Aquaculture Entity where project took place: University of Santiago de Compostela

End date: 28/02/2018

23 Other relevant activities: Training course "Editing scientific texts and presentations with LaTeX"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 20/02/2018

24 Other relevant activities: Training course "Statistics with R for researchers"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 31/10/2017

25 Other relevant activities: Training course "Introduction to Python programming"

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

End date: 09/06/2017

26 Other relevant activities: Creation and periodic publication of advances in aquaculture on the website of the

Marine Genetic Resources group http://rexenmar.webs.uvigo.es/

Entity where project took place: University of Vigo

Scientific and technological experience

Scientific or technological activities

R&D projects funded through competitive calls of public or private entities

1 Name of the project: Reproductive biology of lumpfish (Cyclopterus lumpus): a key to successful selective breeding

Entity where project took place: NOFIMA AS **Type of entity:** Innovation and Technology Centres

City of entity: Tromsø, Norway

Name principal investigator (PI, Co-PI...): Velmurugu Puvanendran; Øyvind J Hansen; Atle Mortensen;

Helge Tveiten

No of researchers: 4

Start-End date: 01/09/2019 - 31/12/2021

2 Name of the project: Digestion and maternal/paternal transfer of microplastic contaminants in Atlantic cod (Gadus morhua) food web

Entity where project took place: NOFIMA AS Type of entity: Innovation and Technology Centres

City of entity: Tromsø, Norway

Name principal investigator (PI, Co-PI....): Velmurugu Puvanendran; Øyvind J. Hansen; Atle Mortensen;

Helge Tveiten

N° of researchers: 4

Start-End date: 01/09/2019 - 31/12/2019

3 Name of the project: Molecular basis of egg quality in Atlantic cod, Gadus morhua

Entity where project took place: NOFIMA AS

City of entity: Tromsø, Norway







Name principal investigator (PI, Co-PI....): Helge Tveiten; Velmurugu Puvanendran; Atle Mortensen;

Øyvind J. Hansen

N° of researchers: 4

Funding entity or bodies:

Ministry of Fisheries and Coastal Affairs of the Royal **Type of entity:** Innovation and Technology Centres

Norwegian Government

City funding entity: Tromsø, Norway Start-End date: 01/09/2019 - 31/12/2019

Scientific and technological activities

Scientific production

Publications, scientific and technical documents

Pérez, M., Fernández-Míguez, M., Matallanas, J. et al. Phylogenetic prospecting for cryptic species of the genus Merluccius (Actinopterygii: Merlucciidae). Sci Rep 11, 5929 (2021). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-85008-9. 15/03/2021.

Type of production: Scientific paper Format: Journal

2 Fernández-Míguez, M., Presa, P., Puvanendran, V., Hansen, Ø. J., Tveiten, H., Mortensen, A. and Pérez, M. Influence of maternal factors on egg quality in the Atlantic cod Gadus morhua (in preparation).

Type of production: Scientific paper

Pita, A., Fernández-Míguez, M., and Presa P. EST-microsatellite types and structural scenarios in European hake fisheries (submitted, August 2021).

Type of production: Scientific paper

4 Fernández-Míguez, M., Pita, A., Gómez, A, and Presa, P. Temporal uncoupling of demographic and genetic metrics for the assessment of the southern stock of Merluccius merluccius (submitted, September 2021).

Type of production: Scientific paper

Works submitted to national or international conferences

1 Title of the work: Microplastics influence expression profiles of genes involved in the reproduction of atlantic cod (Gadus morhua)

Name of the conference: AQUA Europe 2020

Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Online,
Date of event: 12/04/2021
End date: 15/04/2021

Organising entity: European Aquaculture Society

M. Fernández-Míguez; V. Puvanendran; P. Presa; M. Pérez; E. Burgerhout; Helge Tveiten; Katrin Vorkamp;

Øyvind J. Hansen; Gunhild Johansen; Andre Bogevik.

2 Title of the work: GENE EXPRESSION ANALYSIS AS AN INDICATOR OF EGG QUALITY IN ATLANTIC

COD Gadus morhua

Name of the conference: Aqua europe 2019







Corresponding author: Yes

City of event: Berlín, Berlin, Germany

Date of event: 07/10/2019 **End date:** 10/10/2019

Organising entity: European Aquaculture Society

M. Fernández-Míguez; M. Pérez; P. Presa; ; H. Tveiten; Atle Mortensen; Velmurugu Puvanendran.

3 Title of the work: INFLUENCE OF MATERNAL FACTORS ON EGG QUALITY IN ATLANTIC COD Gadus

morhua.

Name of the conference: AQUA 2018

Corresponding author: Yes
City of event: Montpellier, France

Date of event: 25/08/2019 **End date:** 29/08/2019

Organising entity: World Aquaculture Society

City organizing entity: Sorrento, United States of America

Fernández-Míguez, M; Hansen, Ø J.; Presa, P; Pérez, M; Tveiten, H; Atle Mortensen; Velmurugu

Puvanendran.

4 Title of the work: GENETIC STRUCTURE OF THE EUROPEAN HAKE Merluccius merluccius:

FUNCTIONAL TAGS VERSUS NEUTRAL MARKERS

Name of the conference: VI International Symposium on Marine Sciences

Corresponding author: Yes City of event: Vigo, Galicia, Spain

Date of event: 20/06/2018 End date: 22/06/2018

Organising entity: Conferencia de Decanos de Ciencias del Mar de España y Universidades de Ciencias

del Mar

City organizing entity: Vigo, Galicia, Spain

Presa, P.; Pérez, M; Fernández-Míguez, M.; Pita, A; Santafé-Muñoz, A.M.

5 Title of the work: THE IMPACT OF OVERFISHING ON THE GENETIC EFFECTIVE POPULATION SIZE

OF THE EUROPEAN HAKE Merluccius merluccius

Name of the conference: VI International Symposium on Marine Sciences

Corresponding author: Yes City of event: Vigo, Galicia, Spain Date of event: 20/06/2018

End date: 22/06/2018

Organising entity: Conferencia de Decanos de Ciencias del Mar de España y Universidades de Ciencias

del Mar

City organizing entity: Vigo, Galicia, Spain

Fernández-Míguez, M; Rodríguez-Pérez, M. I.; Cuéllar-Pinzón, J.; Pita, A; Pérez, M; Angie M. Santafé

Muñoz; Pablo Presa Martínez.







Other achievements

Stays in public or private R&D centres

Entity: NOFIMA AS Type of entity: R&D Centre

Faculty, institute or centre: Private company

City of entity: Tromsø, Norway

Goals of the stay: Doctorate

Provable tasks: Reproductive design in cod for the analysis of early gene expression



